<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the King, in Christ-Church, Dublin, on Ash-Wednesday 1689 by Fr. Edmond Dulany ...</title>
            <author>Dulany, Edmond.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36821</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2517</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17101</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13645539</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13645539</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100910</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36821)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100910)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 786:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the King, in Christ-Church, Dublin, on Ash-Wednesday 1689 by Fr. Edmond Dulany ...</title>
                  <author>Dulany, Edmond.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>21, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for James Malone ... and are to be sold at his shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published by His Majesties special command."</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew VI, 19 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Ash Wednesday sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100910:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100910:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the KING, IN Chriſt-Church, DUBLIN, On Aſh-wedneſday 1689.</p>
            <p>By Fr. Edmond Dulany, Franciſcan Fryer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by his Majeſties ſpecial Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dublin,</hi> Printed for Alderman <hi>James Malone</hi> Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, and are to be ſold at his shop in <hi>Skinnerrow,</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:100910:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:100910:2"/>
            <head>A Sermon Preached before the KING, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 6.</hi> verſe <hi>19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Nolite Theſaurizare vobis theſaures in terra, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Heap not up to your ſelves Treaſures on the Earth, where the Ruſt and Moth do Corrupt, and where Thieves do digg through and ſteal; But heap to your ſelves Treaſures in Heaven.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>LEt Corruption Enter (moſt Sacred Majeſty) to make a prey of this Frail body when I am ſhut up in the fatal <hi>Tomb,</hi> and buried in the Boſom of <hi>Oblivion,</hi> waiting to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the laſt call of the <hi>Arch-angels</hi> Trumpet to appear before the Tribunal of the dreadful Judgment; Let creeping Worms, Serpents, and on w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ildy Beaſts devour this Fleſh, and leave only my bones the reſidue of their Hunger, to be reſolved into Aſhes by the Revolutions of time, I will ſtill cry with <hi>Diogenes; Quid ferarum mihi nihil femienti oberit Laniatus.</hi> Let man be converted into Duſt, he ſhall have no Pain when he is deſtitute of all ſence of Feeling, it is not the Grave document of the Holy Churches <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento</hi> marking our Foreheads this morning with <hi>Aſhes,</hi> a ſymbol of Mortallity; And the Primitive ingredient that Conſtituts the ſtructure of this Tabernacle, and in which a Reſolution of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100910:3"/> whole ſhall ſoon End; it is nothing of theſe can ſtrike a Terror into my heart, But the Concluſion of the Prophet <hi>Joel,</hi> who from the mouth of God Chalking out the Way we muſt Walk to ſave our Souls, Emphatically Commands us to turn our hearts drunk with the Love of Creatures, to God, and to puniſh by Abſtinence and Faſt, the Rebellion of theſe Members that firſt mutiny'd by conſent, and then by overt Acts warr'd againſt our Soveraigns Laws, <hi>Convertimini ad me in toto corde veſtro, in Jejunio:</hi> And this is not enough, but we muſt waſh the Impurity of our Thoughts with the ſalt tears of our Eyes, and wipe them of with the ſighs and deep groanes of our hearts, <hi>in fletu &amp; planctu,</hi> and the heart that was the Harbor of our Crimes muſt be Rent with grief and ſorrow, <hi>Scindite Corda veſtra;</hi> he proceeds further to tell us that to accompliſh the juſt meaſures of true Repentance, we muſt not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proſcribe the uſe of unlawfull, but alſo temper the uſe of Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things: <hi>Egrediatur ſponſus de Cubili ſuo; Let the Bridegroom go forth of his Chamber, and the Bride out of her Bride-Chamber;</hi> all this is too Little if the Prieſts, the Miniſters of the Lord between the Porch and the Altar, will not weep and cry <hi>parce Domine, parce po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulo tuo: Spare O Lord, ſpare thy People, and give not thine Inheritance into reproach, that the Nations have Dominion over them;</hi> and when all this is done, after we Chaſtize our bodies in the ſevereſt Exerciſes of Mortification, after we afflict our Souls with the deepeſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments of grief for our offences, after we deny our ſelves the uſe of things inoffenſive, and have our cauſe Recommended to Heaven by the Interceſſion and publick Prayers of the Prieſts and Miniſters of God: Let all Sinfull Souls with Dread and Fear, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark what ſlender aſſurance we have from this Organ of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, of the ſecurity of our Salvation when he leaves us ſtill in doubt whether the Lord will Convert and forgive us, <hi>Quis ſcit ſi convertatur et Ignoscat Deus;</hi> O terrible words! if they that leave no Corner of their hearts to entertain any other thoughts, then ſuch as unite them to God in Love and Charity, and deteſt their former faults, can have no aſſureance of the ſecurity of their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, what hopes can thoſe have, that Incloſe all their deſires within the Circle of Wordly Intereſt, and fall into a certain blindneſs and hardneſs that Render them Inſenſible to all the Movements of Grace? how ſure is Hell for thoſe that put up a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100910:3"/> three Headed Idol of Honours, Wealth and Pleaſures in oppoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion to the holy Trinity dedicating thereto, all their thoughts and actions (a practice commonly Following men of Quallity and Courtiers) if thoſe that abdicate dignities, deſpiſe Riches, and lead a life in continual Purgatory of voluntary Chaſtizments upon their own bodies, do labour under a deadly Fear of looſeing Heaven, Finally if the humble penitent, the poor in ſpirit, and the Righteous man cannot determine whether he lyes under the diſgrace or favour of God, <hi>quia nemo ſcit an amore vel odio ſit dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> There is no ground for the ambitious Courtier, the ſenſual Libertine or the Injuſt States-man to expect Salvation. Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men this ought to be the Subject of your Frequent Meditations this Holy time of Lent to Reclaim you in your vanities, to work your Salvation in Trembling fear, that may diſpoſe you to true and ſevere works of Penance and Repentance, and undervalue the deluding and treacherous Honours, Riches and Pleaſures of this Falſe world, by which Milions of Souls do Eternally periſh. It is what the Son of God Commands you to do in the leſſon of the Goſpel read this morning; <hi>Nolite theſaurizare vobis theſauros in ter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and it is what I deſign to perſwade you to; In order to which I will divide this diſcourſe into two parts, The firſt whereof will E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, the vanity of all worldly Treaſures, for which men do expoſe themſelves to Perdition, and the Afflictions that attend them, the ſecond will ſhew their Inconſtancy, and Conclude by Inference from ſuch premiſſes, that they are not fit objects to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt the deſires of a Rational Soul whoſe capacity is of ſo vaſt an Extent that nothing but the Treaſures of Heaven can fill it. This ſhall be the Subject of your Sacred Majeſties favorable attention, which I beg, and the diſcourſe I intend to make, after we Implore the Grace and help of the Holy Ghoſt and ſalute the ever Bleſſed Virgin, with the Archangel <hi>Hayl Mary</hi> &amp;c:</p>
            <p>Before I enter upon the proofes of my divſion, I muſt undeceive any that may miſtake my Intention to leſſen the Credit of true Honours in this world as Contrary to the Inſtitutions of Divine Laws or inveigh againſt Riches as of themſelves repugnant to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, or againſt moderate pleaſures as inconſiſtent with the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal happineſs we aſpire to in the other world: Such Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were ſhoots of Hereſy, Blaſphemy and Cruelty, when the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100910:4"/> of Nature in the firſt draught of the world out of nothing coppied Monarchy (which Implyes all Dignities and Honours) in the perſon of <hi>Adam,</hi> with an abſolute Dominion over all that was Created, and Furniſhed him with plentifull means to ſupport the Grandeur of ſo great a Title, in the Vaſſallage of all the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures he Subjected to his Power, without any Reſtriction in the uſe of any part thereof to gratifie his deſires, except the uſe of the forbidden Tree.</p>
            <p>In the ſtate of corrupt Nature, in which the paſſions of man kindled to an exceſs of unrulineſs, through the loſs of Original Juſtice; Providence ordained the Power of Kings with the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of Greatneſs, which imports a right in them to Command, and impoſes upon all Subjects an indiſpenſable obligation of Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty and Obedience; and in reference to wealth and pleaſures, there is no innovation, only a task of labour and pain, added in the acquiſition, as puniſhment for ſin, and a regular moderation in the uſe, Squared by the Rules of God's Commandments, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of the holy Church, to make it meritorious.</p>
            <p>It is not therefore Honours primarily lodged by Providence &amp; Nature in the perſon of the King, and flowing from him by a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Emanation to others gradually qualified by the merit of their Loyalty, and ſignal ſervices in their many and different ſtations and degrees, that come in diſpute as a ſubject of reflections from the Goſpel of Chriſt: But the corrupt meaſures taken by many that aſpire to them without any other merit than their ambition, and the perverſe uſe made of that Eminence by others; who ought to recede ſo far from any vice, as they are exalted to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach in dignity, to the Prince that confers it; in whoſe Front is ſtampt the Image of God's Power and Authority, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence an obligation to Vertues ſuitable to that Supreme De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree.</p>
            <p>Riches alſo, which were given by the hand of God for the uſe of life, and ought to ſerve us as inſtruments to acquire Heaven, are no further blameable, than they are converted by us into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines, to work Iniquity, as holy <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith; and by our folly, or rather madneſs, are raiſed to ſuch a height of eſteem in our fancies, that baſely forgetting God, the only and true Center of our happineſs, we fix our love uponn them, as the ultimate end to accompliſh all our de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>es.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:100910:4"/>
            <p>God has placed man in an earthly Paradiſe of pleaſure, to give him therein a commencing taſte of thoſe future full contentments he was to enjoy in the Heavenly Paradiſe, after his tranſlation from the Pilgrimage; and though for his diſobedience, he and his poſterity were attainted, and baniſhed from thence, yet in their baniſhment they were not left ſo unhappy, but they had in the midſt of afflictions, ſuch a meaſure of contentments and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in the enjoyment of Creatures, as may in the religious uſe thereof, lead them to conclude the endleſs pleaſures that conſiſt in the fruition of the Creator: But ſuch is the malice and ſtupidity under which men did in all ages, and do labour, that ſhutting their eyes to Reaſon and Religion, without regard to Rewards or Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, to Threatnings or Promiſes, to Heaven or Hell, they make Dignities, Wealth and Pleaſures, the Butt of all their aims, by open and ſecret contrivances, to fill the vacuities of the Civil Body, not to ſtrengthen, but to weaken the parts thereof, often receding through Pride, and wanton Ambition, from their Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to Authority, even to the contempt of Majeſty, in Sedition, and helliſh Rebellions, (of which our Times do afford too woful an experience); and trampling inferiors by violence and extortion, to ſupport their extravagant diſſolution in Debauchery and Luſt, and to ſatisfy their inſatiable thirſt of Covetouſneſs: and thus they ſacrifice Loyalty to their Pride and Ambition in Rebellion, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty to their Avarice in Injuſtice, Vertue to brutiſh Pleaſures in Concupiſcence, their Honour to diſgrace, and their Souls to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.</p>
            <p>To ſecure you from ſuch diſmal ruines, D. C. S. The Saviour of the World gives you a Preſervative, in the preſent Goſpel, <hi>Nolite theſaurizare vobis theſauros in terra, &amp;c. Heap not up to your ſelves Treaſures on Earth, where the Ruſt and Moth do Corrupt, and where Thieves do Digg through and Steal.</hi> Survey all the parts of the treaſures of the earth, upon which man throws the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his heart exceſſively to the contempt of God, and loſs of his Soul, and you ſhall find them perpetually waited on by the ruſt of Vanity, the moth of Afflictions, and the thieves of Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, to corrupt their nature, uſe and permanence. It is the Doctrine of the Holy Ghoſt denounced by the wiſeſt of Kings, and proved by him in the experience of the greateſt treaſures the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100910:5"/> earth could afford; <hi>Superinduxi animae mea cogitationem ſuper omnia illa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. Cap. 2. jux l. G.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; inveni in eis, tria haec vanitatem, afflictionem &amp; conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mationem;</hi> Let covetous men fill their Coffers with the Gold of the new found world, the Pearls fiſhed in the Seas of <hi>Aſia,</hi> the Jewels brought from the remote Regions of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and call it treaſure; Let Honour draw out long liſts of Anceſtors, with exact Records of their Proweſs and Feats, to fill parchment with Titles, and call it Nobility of Blood; Let Nations with ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Bands run to the deſtruction of one another, and the ſubdued ſerve for a foundation to erect Monuments of Triumph to prop the Glory of the Conqueror, and call it Victory: Let the ſelf-intereſted Statesman deviſe new Maxims of Government to puſh forward his own ends, under colour of publick good, though de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to many, and injurious to God and his Church, and call it Policy: Let Pride pleaſe it ſelf in proportion of Parts, and a ſupply to the defect borrowed from a Dreſs, little becoming the Gravity of Chriſtian Religion, or conformable to the Doctrine of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> or the practice of the holy primitive Chriſtians, and call it Beauty All-a-mode: Let Ambition glory in the dependency and flattery of many underlings, and call it Power, in Authority to Command, and adminiſter Laws to others, and call it Dignity, in the plenty of worldly ſubſtance, and call it Riches: Let ſenſuality find new inventions to gratify the guſt of ſenſes, and call it Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: But the Holy Ghoſt, by the mouth of <hi>Solomon,</hi> in all theſe finds nothing but Vanity; <hi>in omnibus inveni vanitatem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt ſtep back from <hi>Solomon</hi> to hear what his Father <hi>David</hi> ſays, in the 42 <hi>Pſalm, Ye ſons of men, how long are you of heavy heart, why love you vanity, and ſeek after lying. Quod mendacium quaritis,</hi> what lying ſeek you after, ſaith holy <hi>Auſtin.</hi> In ſhort, <hi>Mundum,</hi> the World, which is expreſs lying, and open falſhood; this is the reward of all your fatigues. O ſenſeleſs worldling! this is the Hire of all your Labours, this is the Crown of all your Victories, the Fruit of all your Toils, and the Reward of all your Troubles; <hi>Fallit vos quod quaeritis, mendacium eſt quod quaeritis; You imagine the World a Magazin, able to afford all content to your deſires.</hi> When the Holy Ghoſt gives it the Name of an horrible and dreadful Deſart, fill'd with monſtrous rnd blood-thirſting wild Beaſts: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in it, Paſſions and Concupiſcences do rule, without the curb
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100910:5"/> of any Laws, beſet with Thorns and Bryars; becauſe in every ſtop you hit upon ſome Affliction that grieves; Corrupted with the Infection of Peſtilent ayr, becauſe there are Pernicious Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of wicked Livers: darkned with Frightful ſhades, Becauſe it is Governed in Ignorance of Heavenly things: Repleniſhed with Croſs and By-ways to lead Aſtray; becauſe it is full of Errors and perverſe Inſtitutions: wihtout Reſtoratiues to Refreſh our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; becauſe it has no true pleaſures, to quench the thirſt of our deſires: ſounding with the abominable noiſe of unlucky Birds, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is nothing ſo often heard as Contumelies againſt Neighbours, and Blaſphemys againſt the great name of God: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from any Succour, becauſe the miſchances that happen are often incurable: deſtitute of any true Felicity, becauſe it is the ſink of all Evils, <hi>Deſertum vere et aridum et ſterile reputat ſoeculum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne hoc</hi> ſaith venerable <hi>Gilbertus</hi> upon thoſe words of the Canticles.<note place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Quae eſt iſta quae aſcendit per deſertum,</hi> and I muſt Cry with the ſame Author, how is it poſſible that men, Endowed with Reaſon and Profeſſing the Religion of one true and Eternal God, ſhould be drawn by the ſcent of a deſart ſo deſcribed, to love any thing therein contained to the Contempt of God and his Laws in ſuch a meaſure, that all Cures daily applyed by Gods Preaching Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters either propoſeing the joys of Heavenly Glory for a Reward of vertue, or the Imminent danger of Slavery and Miſery, which is viſible and apparent, as a Temporal Correction to Reclaim our Manners, or Eternal fire as the Everlaſting puniſhment of final perſeverance in ſin, are ſo Far from producing in us the deſigned Effects, that all their Endeavours ſeem to be Incentives, rather then Lenitives, to the diſeaſe of ſelf love, &amp; the love of the world, it is grown ſo Epidemical in every State and Condition and Sex and Age.</p>
            <p>Heathens were ſenſible of the vanity of the Worlds gifts, which Chriſtians by their too much value for them, and their Irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous deſires ſeem to deny; this made <hi>Seneca</hi> declare,<note place="margin">Lib. det<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quillitate anim.</note> that all wordly goods were Intrinſecally uniform in vanity, and Extrinſecally dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent only in Form and Figure: Let us hear your ſenſe of this Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, great Apoſtle of the Nations; It paſſeth away ſaith he, It flyeth, It periſheth, <hi>praeterit figura hujus mundi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">J. Cor. 7.</note> like a figure drawn in dry duſt, which for its levity hath no Conſiſtency and is the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100910:6"/> mock-ſtock of winds raiſed by the leaſt blaſt, apt to blind the Eyes,<note place="margin">Cap. 29.</note> and durt, whatever it lights upon; with reaſon then I may ſpeak to the lovers of the world in the words of the Prophet <hi>Eſay:</hi> upon another occaſion <hi>Expergiscimini, Expergiscimini, Qui habitatis in pulvere,</hi> awake awake ye that dwell in the duſt, and open your Eyes to conſider: that in duſt you have layd the Foundation of your might and power, Kings and Monarchs; To the duſt you commit the Glory of your Titles, Noblemen, upon the duſt you Engrave the marks of your Renown, Famous men; in the duſt you leave the footſteps of your Enterprizes Valliant men; It is duſt that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes the ſubſtnace of your Treaſures, Rich men, by the duſt you ſeek to ſatisfie the huger of your deſires voluptuous men, at the duſt you Level all the Eſſays of your projects, Ambitious men; From the duſt you borrowed the firſt material of your being Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al men, and into duſt ſhall ſoon Return thoſe bodies you now Pamper with ſo much delicacy, ſenſual men, which is the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement given you by the Holy Church this morning, <hi>Pulvis es et in pulverem reverteris</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Did you ever obſerve <hi>A. A.</hi> a flock of Innocent Children dally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in the ſand and in ſerious folly, drawing plat-forms of Cities and Towns, here raiſing heaps under the Title of ſtrong Caſtles and Impregnable Forts, there marking long Ridges giving them the name of Trenches and dikes for defence in one place ranging ſmall ſtones in a Row which they call Caſarms to Lodg Soldiers, in another drawing up a certain number to Aſſail the Fortifications and a thouſand other fancies of their Innocent folly, when their Fabrick in fine is but Sand,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Cant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> This is properly the life of Worldly men ſays <hi>Greg. Niſſ: hoc eſt humana vita puerorum ludus in arena &amp;c.</hi> Their Honour is but Sand, their power is but Sand, their wealth is but Sand, and all what the World can give is but Sand, Duſt and Vanity; <hi>In omnibus inveni vanitatem;</hi> what is more vain then a dream, and yet all the Power and Riches and Pleaſures of the Earth are no other thing if you believe the Spirit of God ſpeaking in the mouth of holy <hi>David, Dormierunt ſomnum ſuum et nihil in venerunt omnes viri divitiarum in manibus ſuis</hi> you dream to have found a Treaſure,<note place="margin">Pſal. 75.</note> you are Rich but in a dream only, when you awake inſtead of real Riches, you find your ſelf Loaden with real Poverty, ſo it is ſaith Holy <hi>Auſtin</hi> the Lovers of this world
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100910:6"/> are Lulled a ſleep by its Charms, that they think not of Eternity, and fancy themſelves happy and Rich,<note place="margin">Ang in Pſal. 75. amave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt praſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia et dormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erunt in piſis, praſentibus et illis facta ſunt ipſa praeſentia delicioſa quomodo qui videt perſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium inveni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ſe Theſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> but when their Eyes are open'd by the Watch of Death, true miſery will Correct the Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a dreaming Fancy, and perpetual Poverty, will Curſe the miſtake of vain Imagination, <hi>Somnium illum divitem fecit, Evigilatio Pauperem fecit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Are not the Ambitious then, and the Covetous, and the Voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of this Age infatuated and damnably Mad if they believe, the Imortallity of the Soul, or a Heaven, or a God to venture their Salvation for the purchaſe of things that ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e no real Subſtance but apparent, That are in Effect, but Falſho d and Lying, that are the fruit of this world a Hideous and Horrible deſart, that are but Duſt and Sand, and conſiſt only in an Ex ernal Figure, that Periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and paſſeth away: Or in the Illuſion of a Fantaſtick dream, and that are finally declar'd by Heaven to be nothing but vanity, <hi>in omnibus in veni vanitatem.</hi> Are not theſe <hi>A: A:</hi> ſo many Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that Convince us we ought not to ſix our hearts upon them, nor ſeek after any Treaſures upon Earth in Obedience to the Doctrine of the Saviour of the world in the Text, <hi>Nolite Theſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizare vobis theſauros in terra:</hi> But their vanity might be diſpenſed with, if the Afflictions and Inconſtancy that follow the Treaſures of the world were not overruling arguments of the Folly and Madneſs of thoſe, that Employ their Labours, their Sweat, their Blood, all their deſires, their Thoughts, their Induſtry, their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies &amp; Souls in a purſuit to purchaſe them. They are not only Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacious and Fayned, but alſo Dolorous &amp; Afflicting, they deceive by their vanity, and torment with their miſery. The Roſe is the ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bol of pleaſurs, whence the Carnal Infidels belching their Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous thoughts againſt the Immortallity of Souls, ſaid <hi>Sap.</hi> 2: Let us Crown our ſelves with Roſes before they wither; In Paradiſe, ſaith great <hi>Baſilius</hi> the Roſe was without Thorns to ſhew that contentments there were to have no mixture of Afflictions or Grief;<note place="margin">hom: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rad:</note> But ſince Sin obliged the Earth to bring forth Brambles and Thiſtles, it is Sorrounded with a guard of Thorns, to Symbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize that Afflicting miſchances, are Inſeparable attendants of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man proſperity, without Exemption, in any Degree, Dignity State or Condition, It is Holy <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his application, <hi>Spina ſeptit gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam floris tanquam humana ſpeculum preferens vitae, quae vanitatemper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>functionis
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100910:7"/> ſuae finitimis curarum ſpinis ſaepe Compungat.</hi> Though you ſhould ſhine O Man with the ſplendor of Honours or ſit upon the Throne of Power,<note place="margin">Lib: 3. hex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Cap. 17.</note> or Command the wealth of <hi>Craeſus; Spina ſemper proxima eſt;</hi> The throne is ſtill near you, look over all thoſe things in which men place their happineſs in this world, and you ſhall find that no one thing is free from a peculiar Melancoly oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of Evil that follows it, Honours are perpetually waited on by Envy which often Contrives their diſgrace; Riches by Fears, and Anxieties, Reputation is obnoxious to the venom of detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Pleaſurs do breed diſtempers; Friendſhip is often made uſe of to work Treachery, in Marriages there Raign Jelouſies, and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to their Parents do prove ungratfull <hi>Meca'nas</hi> in Feathers, felt the ſame grief that Tormented <hi>Regulus</hi> upon a <hi>Gibbet</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca,</hi> to hinder his repoſe, <hi>Tam vigilat in pluma, quam Regulus in Cruce.</hi> And <hi>Dioniſius</hi> his Diſhes proved unſavory to his Gueſts, for the Sword that hung over their Heads, ſo unlimitted are the Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries attending the Pleaſurs of the world, that even in the Throne they cannot be divorced: and <hi>Seleveus</hi> Taught by the Experience, declared that whoever knew the weight of the Scepter though of Gold, would not honour it to lift it from the Dunghill, and if Kings and Princes in the midſt of their Might and Power ſunk under the Croſſes and Anguiſhes they endured to ſuch a deſcent of diſreſpectful Expreſſions of the Scepter and Crown, who can Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to find in this world, any true and accompliſhed Felicity, or any ſolid Comfort or Joy? I will not Inſtance the particular Circumſtances of every mans Troubles in the purſuit of that part of the worlds vanity he Ayms at, I will only ſay the acquiſition thereof coſts him greater paines, then the enjoyment gives Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; what labors do not the Covetous undergo for their Riches, The ſenſual Epicures for their Pleaſures, the vain to ſupport their Pride, and the Ambitious to Attain to Dignities?</p>
            <p>The Servants of God in their ſevereſt Acts of Pennance, for the Conqueſt of the Kingdom of Heaven, never Exercized greater Mortifications, then the Lovers of the world ſubmit themſelves to for to attain to their Ends, if they do faſt to Mortify the fleſh, The Covetous do faſt live Cloſe and Uncharitable, to fatten their Purſes; if they go in Pilgrimage for the love of Vertue, what Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage by Sea and Land, do not theſe undertake for the love of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100910:7"/> Gold; if the Servants of God do, watch in Prayer, the diſolute and Intemperate do watch in Debauchery,<note place="margin">Sap. 5.</note> They humble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to all men for Chriſt, and how many do the Ambitious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe themſelves to, Thoſe do lye under the Inclemency of the weather and theſe do Expoſe themſelves, to a Thouſand Storms, Fatigues and Troubles that truth Forces this Confeſſion out of their Mouths <hi>laſſati, ſumus in via Iniquitatis;</hi> we are wearied in the way of Iniquity, Their Suffrings are equal to the Tortures of Martyrs, ſaith holy <hi>Auſtin;</hi> but their merits, are different, and their ends are diſform, <hi>Similes penae ſed diſcreta Cauſa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The world is a Pallace like that in which <hi>Job's</hi> Children Feaſted which within the ſpace of one houer, ſaith holy <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hom: ſ. in Job.</note> was a dwelling place of the living, and a grave of the Dead, a Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queting houſe of Friends, and a Burying place of the defunct, a Choire of Muſick, and the Stage of a moſt wofull Tragedy: <hi>una eademquae hora Domus et Sepulchrum, convivium et Tumulus, feſtum et fletus, facia eſt;</hi> Even ſo ſaith holy <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> the world invites its Lovers to feaſt in the plenty of its pleaſures; but Treacherous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppreſſes them with unexpected Ruine it invites them to Dine and drags them to dye, it promiſſes meat, and Furniſhes Afflictions, pretends to give wine, and fills the Cup with poyſon. <hi>Rogas ad Convivium, Cogis ad mortem;</hi> It affords Treaſures that can never be Enjoyed, but in a flood of real evils,<note place="margin">Invitas ad prandium ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre vjs ad ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchrum; ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bos promittis et tormenta irrogas; vina praetendis, et venena ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundis. Lib. de Elia et jej<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> it offers fruit that cannot be gathered without a Crop of Infinit Troubles, it promiſſes hapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and at the ſame time uſhers in miſeries, it flatters by its Smiling and Murthers by its Creſſes. <hi>Cum oblectant, ſa'viunt, Cum blandiuntur occidunt.</hi> I will Conclude this firſt part by the words of holy <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> what can be more unhappy then that man created for Glory ſhall Enſlave his heart in the diſordered deſire of Terrene things, and throwing away the Badges of his Liberty, and Nobillity, ſhall fall from Celeſtial things to think or ſpeak of nothing, but of Dignities ſubject to the Ruſt of Vanitys, or Riches, that ſtill carry in them the Moth of Gnawing Afflictions,<note place="margin">val. hom. 6.</note> or of Pleaſurs that fix a ſting in the Soul, when they Power Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in the Mouth.</p>
            <p>What Villany is it for love of theſe to Trample the poor, to oppreſs the Innocent, to Enjure the Widdow to ſtrip the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan, to ſuck the Blood of the Weaker, To Rob the Church of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100910:8"/> her Rights, To confound Order To forget God, To Tranſgreſs his Commandments, To Renounce his Glory, To Contemn his promiſes to deſpiſe his Menaces, to offend his love, to Exaſperate his Juſtice, to provoke his Anger, and to draw his Malediction. Chriſtian Souls, if the Vanity and Afflictions inſeperable from the Treaſurs of the world, which are purſued with ſo much vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence and diſorder, cannot work upon other mens hearts to divert them, at leaſt let Prudence direct you, not to affect Immoderatly or unlawfully deſire thoſe things which you are not ſure to retain when you have them, It is Vertuous and Meritorious to draw, your affections, from them before you are Compelled by a certain ſure neceſſity to quit them with grief and Confuſion, for they are Unſtable, and Inconſtant, which is the matter of my</p>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>Second Part.</head>
               <p>Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his 29th Sermon <hi>de v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rbis domini</hi> puts this queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all thoſe that Throw their Affections upon the World to the Contempt of Gods Laws, and without Regard to the Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Souls <hi>Cur ponimus Cor in terra, Cum videamus quia ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur Terra;</hi> why do we abandon our hearts to the Irregular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and Concupiſence of Terrene Treaſurs which we know are Inſtable and Tranſitory? why do we pretend to reſt our ſelves upon that which we ſee is in continual Turbulent Motion towards its own deſtruction, and the Ruin of thoſe that Rely upon it, or why do men Confide in, or Truſt to that which they finde by daily Experience to deceive and betray?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Velut nubes pertranſiit ſalus mea,</hi> ſaith holy <hi>Iob,</hi> The true pattern of patient Princes deſcribing his own miſfortune and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Fall from the Glory of the Throne to the miſery of the dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill,<note place="margin">Job. Cap. 30 v. 15.</note> my proſperity, my Riches, and all my glory hath paſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way like a cloud, The comparlſon and <hi>Simile,</hi> cannot be more proper, having for an Author the holy <hi>Ghoſt,</hi> which moved the Organs of this great Saint to Expreſs it, a Cloud then in it's Effects and Nature is the Right Symbol of Human proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100910:8"/> and the perfect emblem of the Great Men of the Earth: For as the clowds mitigate the rayes of the ſcorching Sun, and refreſhes ſublunary things, apt to ſuffer by the over-much heat of that Planet; ſo Powerful Men are the defence of thoſe that are under their protection, from the heat of injury and oppreſſion; a fertil clowd ſhowring, recreates the barren and dry ground, and revives decaying flowers and fruits: A Prince by the influence of his Favours gives vigor to, and revives his Subjects, drooping under the yoke of adverſities: A clowd kindled, often darts in the air, terrible torches, and wild flames. This repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents an angry Potentate of the Earth, when he terrifies with a fire caſt from his eyes, and with lightnings from his Countenance. A clowd armed with unuſual hail, ſtorms, tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, oppreſſes innocent trees, vines, plants; and is not this the figure of an Uſurping Tyrant, threatning without reſerve, deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, ſlaughter, and ſlavery; and when a Cloud roars in Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and diſcharges dreadful flaſhes of Lightnings, againſt which humane providence can make no defence; ſhall not we ſay, This reſembles the wild reſolutions of ſuch a Monſter in his decrees againſt Loyal Subjects, for adhering to God's Anointed, their lawful and natural Prince: But what is the nature and ſubſtance of this Cloud, that works ſuch prodigious effects? A little va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour raiſed from the low region of the earth,<note place="margin">Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys.</note> and originally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted from the tribe of Pools and Sinks, elevated chiefly by its own levity, to the ſecond region of the Air;<note place="margin">By Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion.</note> and what prop ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtains it there? nothing but a Pillar of ſlender Air, which is no ſolid Prop; and how long can it laſt, or pretend to ſubſiſt? no longer than it is calm weather about it; the firſt blaſt of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary wind that blows towards it, will drive, diſſipate, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it. This is the true figure of the Power and Greatneſs of the Ambitious of the Earth; ſaith holy <hi>Gregory,</hi> a Cloud that va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes of a ſudden, and hath not a monent of aſſured permanence; they are high and ſublime, raiſed above others, to the ſecond re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the air: but the foundation that ſupports them, is weak and unſtable; one blaſt of popular commotion, or misfortune, breaks them; one fit of diſtemper levels them to the ground, and brings all their Greatneſs to their primitive duſt in the grave; <hi>Salus ergo ut nubes tranſiit quia peccatorum gloria quae alta eſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 20. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</note> 
                  <hi>fixa non eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:100910:9"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ab exemplo.</note>Liſt your eyes, D. C. to view that ever curſed, impious and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural <hi>Abſolom,</hi> famous in infamy, ſwelled with helliſh pride, and with ſacrilegious arms, embarking himſelf in the ocean of bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Ambition, to Uſurp his Fathers Throne, ready to Imbrew his inhumane hands in the Blood of the beſt of Kings, and eviſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the kindeſt of Fathers. Obſerve a thrice perjured people ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by a Nobility drunk with the love of diſſolution and riot, and poyſon'd with the venom of Diſloyalty and Rebellion, ſuckt from the corrupt principles of a reſtleſs Religion, ſetting him up a Mimick King, under the Royal Canopy, to receive homage from Vaſſals, tribute from Subjects, and Embaſſies from foreign Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: He models Governments, promulges Laws, eſtabliſhes Prag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks, puniſhes, rewards, exalts, depoſes, impoveriſhes, enriches, condemns, pardons. Unfortunate man, what do you do? how far will your Ambition dragg you? againſt a King that derives his Power from Heaven, and not from Men, you turn your ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious arms? againſt a Father, you deviſe your ſtratagems? &amp; to attain to his Crown, you arrived to the height of iniquity, treading under foot the Laws of God, and Man, and Nature; you are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate, whether you win or loſe; if you prevail, you are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious; if you miſs, you are infamous; if you overcome, you ſhall ever be accurſt, to have gained a Victory more diſhonourable and inglorious than the loſs can be; if you loſe, you ſhall ever lye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the confuſion juſt judgment will bring upon you for entring into ſo unjuſt and unnatural a War; if you vanquiſh, you forfeit the beſt Jewel Nature could ſet in your breaſt, which is the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude you ought a good Father; if you be ſubdued, your loſs will not be only of life, (that is too ſmall a ſatisfaction for your guilt;) nor of your credit or reputation, (for we ſee how little you value it) but of your Soul, and eternal Salvation, to expiate in everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing flames, the enormity of your execrable Ambition. Behold, Chriſtians, O juſt Judgment of the Almighty! This Parricide, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Miſcreant, in the midſt of his vaſt and ill-grounded hopes, carried on more by the violence of his wicked deſigns, than the force of the Beaſt he rid on, was leſt hanging upon a Tree, by the hair of his head, and pierc'd through the heart with three Jave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins, and covered with wounds over all his Body, he fell to end the infamy of his actions in the cataſtrophe of a deſerved diſmal
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100910:9"/> death. Imprecations are not juſtifiable in a Pulpit, yet it were but Juſtice, O Heavens,<note place="margin">Let the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of my Lord the King become as the Child <hi>(Abſalom)</hi> and all that riſe againſt him unto evil, 2 <hi>Reg.</hi> 18.</note> that Equals in Impiety ſhould be ſoon equalled in puniſhments; that a re-acceſſion to his Throne may be facilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Juſt and Godly <hi>David.</hi> But this with ſubmiſſion to thy holy will, be ſaid, O Lord! whoſe hidden decrees permitting Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety to rule, we are to receive, and accept of without repining, in perfect reſignation; knowing that what thou ordaineſt, is moſt available to us, and that thou art merciful and good, to make us happy even by our adverſities, which thou canſt turn to our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, when we truly ſubmit our ſelves in conformity to thy Divine pleaſure. Now what we are to gather from the fatal courſe of Impious <hi>Abſalom</hi> to our purpoſe, is the impiety of irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Ambition,<note place="margin">Lib. 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> cap: 18. Drogo.</note> and the inconſtancy of the Greatneſs promiſed by this falſe world; <hi>Illo ſuſpenſo inter Coelum &amp; Terram, mulus cui inſederat pertranſit,</hi> ſaith the ſacred Text; <hi>(Abſalom)</hi> hanging between Heaven and Earth: The mule that he rid upon paſſed through, <hi>pertranſit,</hi> ſaith an Excellent Author, becauſe the world paſſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with its concupiſcence in great ſpeed: which inconſtancy prompted the Eloquence of <hi>Rome</hi> to break out in Exclamations worthy to be printed in the hearts of true Believers: <hi>O fallacem hominum ſpem, fragilem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fortunam, &amp; inanes noſtras contentiones quae in medio ſpatio ſaepe franguntur, &amp; corruunt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. de O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp; ante in ipſo curſu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruuntur quam portum conſpicere potuerunt;</hi> O vain hopes of mortal men, that ſeek with ſo much heat and ſtrife to eſtabliſh your hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs upon the beguiling falſe goods of the earth, which are moſt apt to forſake and deſert you when you ſeem to be moſt ſure of them. Thoſe Honours and Treaſures that puff you up with Pride, ſaith <hi>Seneca, Neſcis ubi te reli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tura ſint,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> you know not where and in what miſerable condition they may ſoon leave you, and that Fortune which you with ſo much injuſtice and oppreſſion ſtrive to ſettle upon poſterity, will be eaſier purchaſed than pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, ſaith <hi>Tacitus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Anna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Such is the volubility and uncertainty of ſublunary things. If we had time to reflect upon the practice of Heathen Philoſophers, in reference to the world, following only the dictates of reaſon, without hopes of future felicity, we ſhould find their moral vertues, and contempt of the world to fix an everlaſting ignominy upon the Chriſtian of our Age, who by their too much love of Honour, Wealth and Pleaſures, and are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:100910:10"/> ſcandal to Chriſt, and an infamy to Religion: our Profeſſion ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges us to Humility, Juſtice, and Temperance, and in a word, to a conformity in our lives and converſation to Chriſt; and this conformity is ſo abſolutely neceſſary, that it is the notion and character of a predeſtinate ſoul, according to the rule given by St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the 8th to the <hi>Romans, Quos praeſcivit &amp; praedeſtinavit conformes fieri imaginis filii ſui, whom he hath foreknown, he hath alſo predeſtinated to be made conformable to the Image of his Son.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An intruſion by Ambition into publick Offices either Civil or Eccleſiaſtical, ſollicited by ſiniſter and unlawful means, and the Pride that makes men once qualified in thoſe ſtations inacceſſible and moroſe to inferiors, which they look upon with ſcorn, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve me,) carries but little marks of Chriſtian Humility, or conformity to the pattern Chriſtians are obliged to copy in their lives.</p>
               <p>Contentions and Diviſions frequently fomented by Envy and Emulation among men, not of the inferior rank, but of the beſt quality, reliſhes more of Sathans confuſed Empire, than the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt, which cannot conſiſt but of members united in Peace and Charity, nor can we expect a Bleſſing from Heaven, if Diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntions and Animoſities, National and Provincial diſtinctions break the tyes of Charity, which by Divine Inſtitutions is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in the eſſential life of Chriſtian Perfection:</p>
               <p>The diſſolution and liberty of ſome of this Age that wallow in the abominatlon of Luſt and Senſuality, is grown to ſuch a pitch of Iniquity, that to have committed enormous Crimes, ſeems too ſmall a ſatisfaction to their brutiſh Voluptuouſneſs, if they do not blaze their infamous actions, glorying in them, to inſtill the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of corruption into the hearts of others, and to encourage them by their perverſe Examples, to become Impious.</p>
               <p>What is the Concuſſion of Magiſtrates, the prevarication of Advocates, the frauds of Merchants, the exactions of Uſurers, the cheats of Tradeſmen, the extortion of Souldiers, and the oppreſſion of the Poor b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Powerful and Rich; but a general defection from, and a deformity to the Law and Examples of Chriſt, and a combination with the Devil, the World, and the Fleſh, to receive at their hands what Almighty God by his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Commandments forbids us to uſurp.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:100910:10"/>
               <p>D. C. I will only offer you two ſhort conſiderations upon the whole matter, and then conclude. The firſt is, that all the Treaſures of the world are vain, afflicting, and inconſtant in this life, as I have ſhewed; they are but a vapour that vaniſh's in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that precludes the paſſage to eternal felicity, that hides from us the incomprehenſible ſplendor of perpetual light, that robs men of the true knowledge of Celeſtial Bliſs, that finally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prives us of the Honour of everlaſting Glory, and are followed in the other World by immortal diſgrace, endleſs miſery,<note place="margin">Bern. Epiſt. 103.</note> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite torments; <hi>Vapor eſt ad modicum parens quod aeternae faelicitatis adytum intercludit, quod perennis luminis in circumſcriptam claritatem abſtondit, quod univerſitatis ſcientia fraudat, quod ſummae privat dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis honore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Second is that the Soul of Man is of ſo vaſt a Capacity in the Extent of its deſires, that it cannot be adjuſted or filled by any thing the world can afford; which every Man may find to be true by his proper Experince of an Inclination that Aims at ſome further Contentment, which he ſtill wants in whatever Degree or Condition he can be in, whereby it is manifeſt, that the accompliſhment of his happineſs Conſiſts in ſomthing above Nature, and this is determined by Faith and Religion, to be the Viſion and Fruition of God, from theſe two Conſiderations, This Inference Rationally follows; Therefore Men ought not to ſeek their happineſs in Natural things, or fix upon them an aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ction Incompatible, with the duty they owe the Acquiſition of that Supreme and Supernatural Felicity, which only ought to be the mark of our Aim in all our Actions, and theſe are the two docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that fill up the Two parts of my Text; <hi>Nol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te</hi> ctc. <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p not up to your ſelves Treaſurs on Earth, where the Raſt and Moth do Corrupt, and the Thieves digg through and ſteal; But heap to your ſelves treaſurs in Heaven</hi> where your Riches will be ſecured, where fraud cannot Circumvent you, nor Chance betray you, nor viciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude overthrow the Eſtabliſhment of your happineſs, nor time make a change in the Bleſſed ſtate of your affairs nor none other of the Domeſtick Enemies of the Earth, diſturb the Poſſeſſion of your full content and joy.</p>
               <p>The Circumſtance of time, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the preſent ſtate of Affairs are two grand re-inforcements upon the obligation we have not to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100910:11"/> defer our obedience to this Sacred Command. The Church Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes our Saviour Faſting and Praying forty dayes, which no Neceſſity could oblige him to, having no Sins to Expiate, but to leave us an Example to follow in the Auſterities of a Mortified life, to make Satisfaction for the Crimes We Committed by Exceſs.</p>
               <p>The State is Threatned with no leſs then a Totall Ruine, and an abſolute overthrow, which never happened to any Kingdom but for unpuniſhed Sins; it is therefore the Intereſt of our Souls and Bodies to Reform our manners, and to Conform our ſelves to the life of our Savior in this holy time, in Faſt and Prayer; To make our publick and private Continual humble Addreſſes to Heaven for the preſervation of his moſt S: M: and the Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his Affairs, to avert from him and us the Fatall blow; Threatned by a proud Uſurping Enemy, whom we need not fear, if we pacifie the wrath of God by true Pennance and Repentance, and an amendment of our lives, it is the beſt Preparation we can make to have good Succeſs in War: Let every man therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin the Lent from his peace made with God in the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Pennance, Let us Reſolve to obey thoſe that are in Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over us, to undergo hardſhip and labors, and when occaſion of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to overcom or dye. It was the Maxim of wiſe Heathens to preſerve Kingdoms and Cities, <hi>Parere magiſtratibus patientem eſſe laborum, et in praelio vincere aut mori,</hi> as <hi>Plutarch</hi> tells us of the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ans,</hi> how much more ought it to be the Rule of Chriſtians, who are in Conſcience oblidged to obey their King, and defend his Crown and Dignity to the laſt drop of their Blood, and to the loſs of their Lives and Fortunes.</p>
               <p>It were to be whiſhed that ſuch as are Members of our Army had as ſtrong a Senſe of Honor and Conſcience to diſcharge their duty with Courage, Care, Vigilancy and Circumſpection, as they have itch of promotion; which ſort of Ambition as it is Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable in a Soldier that Strives by his Actions to make himſelf worthy of preferment, ſo in thoſe that Act Sluggiſhly like Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick mercenaries, it is no leſs infamous then Damnable, whereas faults Committed in that duty, do tend to diſhonor God, to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne the King, to Expoſe him to the Fury of his Blood-thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Enemies, to betray the Country, and to baniſh Religion, I
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100910:11"/> wiſh all Officers did firſt Conceive a horror againſt any thing that may bring them under ſuch black Helliſh Charracters, and then make the Impreſſion upon thoſe that are under their Command, to prevent loſſes that may not be retrieved, and Leſſen the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, of ſo frequent Seſſions of Courts Martial as we ſee, whoſe punitive ſentence perpetually brands the accuſed with an infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my if not Really deſerved, at leaſt Commonly believed and Suſpected.</p>
               <p>And to accompliſh all things that may Earn a Bleſſing to our Cauſe: S: M. let Ambition, Partiality and double dealings by your Commands, be Baniſhed from the Court: Let not the Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty men of your State make your Laws a Spiders Webb to Catch and Devour the ſmall Flies, and let the Bigg ones paſs untouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Leſt the Cry of <hi>Orphans,</hi> the groans of <hi>Widdows,</hi> and the <hi>Blood</hi> of the <hi>Injured poor;</hi> ſhould call for Vengeance to Heaven and Obtain it. Let not <hi>Lent</hi> be Converted to a Carnaval in the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of great Men, nor the Tables be Loaden with Superfluous Diſhes, to feed Lackeys and Foot-boys even to Gluttony, and the Poor of Chriſt Languiſhing in the Street ſtarving for Want of Bread, Let not the Taverns be Crowded from Morning to Night, and the Churches and Chapels of God left waſte, let E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and Juſtice govern the Bench without Partiality or Reſpect of Perſons, Let Conſcience overule the Covetouſneſs of Exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dealers; Let modeſty in Apparel, ſpare ſomt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing to cover Chriſt naked in the perſons of the poor, Let Blaſphemous Tongues learn from juſt Chaſtiſements to bear Reſpect to the holy name of God. Let publick puniſhments ſuppreſs the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of publick ſcandals, let Chriſtian Diſcipline put an End to Antichriſtian diſſolution which Raing'd theſe many years among us, and Finally let the love of Heaven proſcribe and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh from our Hearts the diſordered love of Creatures, of vain Dignities, Afflicting Riches, and Inconſtant pleaſurs, that Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Ruling our Actions here in Grace may lead us to Triumph in Everlaſting Glory. which I wiſh your S. M. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and all your Faithfull Subjects.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:100910:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page three line 1. read <hi>Theſauros.</hi> ibid l. 11. r wild beaſts, pag. 4. l. 32 inſtead of then, r. but. pag. 7. l. 11 r. and ſtill do labour pag. 8 l. 27 r. 4th pſalm. pag. 10 l. 11 r. ſubſtance. <hi>ibid.</hi> l. 12 r. hunger. <hi>ibid.</hi> l. 23 after defence, put a point. pag. 11 r. in the margin <hi>praeſentia et dormierunt in ipſis preaſentibus. ibid.</hi> l. 16 <hi>A. A.</hi> ſignifies <hi>Chriſtian Auditors.</hi> pag. 12 l. 4 r. thorn. pag. 13 l. 19 after Ruine, put a period. <hi>ibid.</hi> l. 26 r. Careſſes. <hi>ibid.</hi> l 34 r. pour.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100910:12"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
